Guide to the Departments and Academic Divisions Reference Collection, 1904-ongoing UA.01.11.0062
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Departments and Academic Divisions Reference collection
1904-ongoing
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. University Archives
UA.01.11.0062
4.5 Linear Feet
approx. 3500 Items
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Departments and Academic Divisions Reference Collection was acquired over time by the University Archives.
Collection Overview
The Departments and Academic Divisions Reference Collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research. This collection includes materials about departments, centers, programs, sections, institutes, cooperative programs (mostly Duke-UNC), and a few other units. These last ones are in the series titled Others and are things that did not fit anywhere else. For instance, School of Spanish Studies was not a school in the sense we now use the term. There are also files on the Woman's College and School of Nursing. The department is the basic academic administrative unit in Arts and Sciences, the Pratt School of Engineering, and the School of Medicine. Historically, other instructional and research units have included those designated as Office of ... and ... Laboratory, as in, for example, the Parapsychology Laboratory. Institutes, Programs, and Centers are academic units created to foster interdisciplinary work. Sections were created in 1988 to facilitate the development of new academic efforts of limited size in subject areas where the creation of a department was not warranted.
The collection includes printed matter, clippings, handbooks, newsletters, flyers, reports, lists of department administrators and other material for many departments/academic divisions at Duke University. Departments with larger amounts of material have their own reference collections. This collection ranges in date from 1904-ongoing.
Related Material
Nicholas School of the Environment Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
School of Engineering Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
Graduate School Reference Collection
Duke University Archives
Clippings (information artifacts); Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. University Archives; Duke University -- Handbooks, manuals, etc.
- Departments
  - Aesthetics, Art and Music, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1942-1960 (Box 1)
  - Aesthetics, Art and Music, Dept. of, 1947-1958, undated (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Studies, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1971-1977 (Box 1)
  - Afro-American Studies, Dept. of, 1990s-2001 (Box 1)
  - Air Force ROTC, Dept. of Aeorspace Studies, 1948- (Box 1)
  - Anthropology, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1972-1978 (Box 1)
  - Anthropology, Dept. of, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Art, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1938-1978 (Box 1)
  - Art, Dept. of, 1961-1998, undated (Box 1)
  - Asian and African Languages and Literature, Dept. of, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Biology, Dept. of [see also Botany, Zoology], 1993 (Box 1)
  - Botany, Dept. of
    - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 1)
    - Memoranda, 1968, 1972, undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 1)
    - Tenure Track Faculty, 1904-2000 (Box 1)
    - Jessica Harland Jacobs' Balancing Tradition and Innovation: The History of Botany at Duke University, 1849-1996 (Box 1)
    - Circa 1980s (Box 1)
  - Chemistry, Dept. of
    - Administration (list), 1973-1987 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1980s, 1991, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Printed Material (Box 1)
  - Classical Studies, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1937-1962 (Box 1)
  - Classical Studies, Dept. of, 1962-ongoing (Box 1)
  - Computer Science, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1971-1978 (Box 1)
  - Computer Science, Dept. of, 1980-ongoing (Box 1)
  - Economics, Dept. of
    - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 1)
    - Circa 1960s-ongoing (Box 1)
    - Clippings, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 1)
    - Graduate Study in Economics Directories, 1964-1979 (Box 1)
    - Graduates Newsletter, 1954-1989 (incomplete) (Box 1)
    - Oeconophile, newsletter, 1973-1979 (Box 2)
    - Duke Economics Review, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Education, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 2)
  - Education, Dept. of, 1960-ongoing (Box 2)
  - English, Dept. of
    - General, 1968-ongoing (Box 2)
    - Clippings, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 2)
    - Six Duke One-Acts, undated (Box 2)
    - Dissertations and Theses, 1930-1962 (lists) (Box 2)
    - Clarence Gohdes' Pioneers in English at Trinity and Duke, 1988 (Box 2)
  - Geology, Dept. of [see also Nicholas School of the Environment Reference Collection] - Administration (list), 1950-1978 (Box 2)
  - Germanic Languages and Literature, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 2)
  - Germanic Languages and Literature, Dept. of, 1973-ongoing (Box 2)
  - Health, Physical Education and Recreation, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1931-1978 (Box 2)
  - Health, Physical Education and Recreation, Dept. of, 1908-ongoing (Box 2)
  - History, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 2)
  - History, Dept. of, 1986-ongoing (Box 2)
  - Management Services, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1967-1978 (Box 2)
  - Management Services, Dept. of, 1976-1978 (Box 2)
  - Mathematics Dept. - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 3)
  - Mathematics Dept., 1979-ongoing (Box 3)
  - Music, Dept. of
    - Administration (list), 1939-1978 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1976-1990s (Box 3)
    - Ciompi Quartet, 1971-ongoing (Box 3)
    - Collegium Musicum, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - Concerts and Seminars, 1953-ongoing (Box 3)
    - General, 1975-ongoing (Box 3)
    - Gina Bachauer Memorial Master Classes, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
    - String School, 1977-1985 (Box 3)
  - Navy ROTC, Dept. of Naval Sciences - Administration (list), 1951-1978 (Box 3)
  - Navy ROTC, Dept. of Naval Sciences, 1972, 1980, 1983, 1991 (Box 3)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of - Administration, 1936-1978 (Box 3)
  - Philosophy, Dept. of, circa 1970s-1980s (Box 3)
  - Physics, Dept. of
    - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3)
    - General, 1946-ongoing (Box 3)
    - Horst Meyer's History of Low Physics at Duke University, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Political Science, Dept. of
    - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 3)
    - General, 1934- (Box 3)
    - Curriculum, 1958- (Box 4)
    - Interuniversity Consortium for Political Research, 1971- (Box 4)
    - Report, 1963 (Box 4)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 4)
  - Psychology, Dept. of, 1996-1997, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Public Policy Sciences, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1972-1978 (Box 4)
  - Religion, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1937-1978 (Box 4)
  - Religion, Dept. of, 1982-ongoing (Box 4)
  - Romance Languages, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 4)
  - Romance Languages, Dept. of, 1981-1982, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Slavic Languages and Literature, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1957-1978 (Box 4)
  - Slavic Languages and Literature, Dept. of, 1968-ongoing (Box 4)
  - Sociology, Dept. of, Administration, 1936-1941, 1972-1978 (Box 4)
  - Sociology, Dept. of, 1972-ongoing (Box 4)
  - Sociology and Anthropology, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1941-1972 (Box 4)
  - Zoology, Dept. of - Administration (list), 1936-1978 (Box 4)
  - Zoology, Dept. of, 1949-1990s (Box 4)
- Centers
  - Africa and the Media, Center for, 1997 (Box 4)
  - Cerebrovascular Research, Center for, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Chemical Biology, Center for, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Cognitive Neuroscience, Center for, 2000 (Box 4)
  - Corporate Economics and Strategy, Center for - Clipping, 1982 (Box 4)
  - Demographic Studies, Center for, 1973-1975, 1992, 2001 (Box 4)
  - Documentary Studies, Center for, 1990s-2001 (Box 4)
  - Environmental Solutions, Center for, 2000-2001 (Box 4)
  - Health Policy Research and Education, Center for, 1991 (Box 4)
  - Health and Clinical Policy, Center for, 1982, 1984 (Box 4)
  - International Development Research, Center for, 1988 (Box 4)
  - International Studies
    - Calendars, 1995-1997 (Box 4)
    - Comparative Studies of Immigration and Ethnicity, Clippings, 1981 (Box 4)
    - General, 1966-1970s (Box 5)
    - General, 1980s-ongoing (Box 5)
    - Program in Comparative Institutions and Systems, Clipping, 1968 (Box 5)
    - Report, 1988-1991 (Box 5)
    - Quebec Studies Program, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
  - Judaic Studies, Center for, 1980s-1990s (Box 5)
  - Late Ancient Studies, Center for - flyer, undated (Box 5)
  - Medieval and Renaissance Studies, Center for - Clippings, 1982, 1986 (Box 5)
  - Resource and Environment Policy Research, Center for, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Science Education, Center for, 1991, 1993 (Box 5)
  - Southern Studies, Center for, 1965-1967 (Box 5)
  - Study of Aging and Human Development, Center for, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 5)
  - Study of Ancient Near Eastern Civilization and Christian Origins, International Center for the, 1980 (Box 5)
  - Study of Energy Conservation, Center for the - Seminar Energy Conservation in Buildings, 1975 (Box 5)
  - Study of the Family and the State, Center for the, 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - Teaching and Learning, Center for, 1990s-2000 (Box 5)
  - Tropical Conservation, Center for, undated (Box 5)
  - Commonwealth and Comparative Studies Center, 1956, 1961, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Japanese Study Center, 1980 (Box 5)
  - John Hope Franklin Center for Interdisciplinary and International Studies, 1999-ongoing (Box 5)
  - North American Studies Center, 1997, 1999 (Box 6)
  - Primate Center, 1970s-ongoing (Box 6)
  - Superfund Basic Research Center, 2000 (Box 6)
- Programs
  - Comparative Area Studies Program, circa 1973, 1979-1980 (Box 6)
  - Dance Program, 1988-1994 (Box 6)
  - Drama Program
    - Clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
    - Duke Players, 1955-1998 (Box 6)
    - Theater Reviews, 1990s-ongoing (Box 6)
  - Duke in New York Program - Calliope, 1983 Oct. (Box 6)
  - Film and Video, Program in, 1989-2002 (Box 6)
  - Genetics, Program in - Administration (list), 1969-1978 (Box 6)
  - Information Science and Information Studies Program, 2000 (Box 6)
  - International Policial Economy, Program in - Clipping, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Islamic and Arabian Development Studies Program, 1977-1985 (Box 6)
  - Literature Program, 1970s, 1990s (Box 6)
  - Markets and Management Program - Clipping, 2000 (Box 6)
  - Neuroscience Program, 1986 (Box 6)
  - Science, Technology and Human Values, Program in, 1979-1983, undated (Box 6)
  - Study of Sexuality, Program in the [certificate program], 1997 (Box 6)
  - Summer Programs, 1980s-1990s (Box 6)
  - Technology and the Liberal Arts Program - Clipping, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Twentieth Century America Program, 1977-1978 (Box 6)
  - University Writing Program, 1995-1996 (Box 6)
- Cooperative Programs
  - Center for World Environment and Sustainable Development, 1991 (Box 6)
  - Cooperative Oceanographic Program - Clipping, 1980 (Box 6)
  - Cooperative Program in the Humanities, 1963-1969 (Box 6)
  - Cooperative Program in International Studies, 1967 (Box 7)
  - Cooperative Program in Judaic Studies, 1973-1977 (Box 7)
  - Cooperative Program in Russian and East European Studies, 1967-1972 (Box 7)
  - Cooperative Program in Teacher Education
    - General, 1959-1967 (Box 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1960-1962 (Box 7)
    - Annual Reports, 1963-1967 (Box 7)
  - Duke-UNC
    - Center for Soviet and East European Studies, [1991] (Box 7)
    - Cooperative Program in East Asian Studies, 1968-1969 (Box 7)
    - Program in Latin American Studies, 1994 (Box 7)
    - Slavic Colloqium, 1967-1968 (Box 7)
    - Women's Studies Research Center, 1981-1988 (Box 7)
  - Research in Judaeo-Christian Antiquity, Office for, 1969-1973 (Box 7)
- Institutes
  - Asian/Pacific Studies Institute
    - Clippings and News Releases, 1980-ongoing (Box 7)
    - Brochures and Announcements, 1956-ongoing (Box 7)
    - Newsletters, 1996-2002 (Box 8)
  - Duke Institute for Learning in Retirement (now the Osher Lifelong Learning Institute)
    - General, 1977-ongoing (Box 8)
    - Catalogs, 1991, 1997-2001 (Box 8)
    - Ten Year Report, 1987 (Box 8)
  - Institute for Genome Sciences and Policy, 2000-ongoing (Box 8)
  - Institute of Statistics and Decision Sciences - Clippings, 1985 (Box 8)
  - Institute of the Arts, 1981-ongoing (Box 8)
  - Kenan Institute for Ethics, 2000-ongoing (Box 8)
  - Sanford Institute, 1972-2008
    Scope and Contents note
    Formerly The Instutute of Policy Sciences and Public Affairs (1972-1991) and The Sanford Institute of Public Policy (1991-2009). Currently The Sanford School of Public Policy, 2009-.
    - General, 1980s-1990s (Box 8)
    - A Statement of Purpose for Political Parties, circa 1981 (Box 8)
    - Brochure and Reports, 1972-1998 (Box 8)
    - Center for Documentary Photography, circa 1990s (Box 8)
    - Center for International Development Research, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Center for North Carolina Policy Research - Cliiping, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Clippings and News Releases, 1971-Ongoing (Box 8)
    - DeWitt Wallace Center, circa 1985-ongoing (Box 8)
    - Faculty Publications, 1982-1996 (Box 9)
    - Governors Center, 1980s-1990s (Box 9)
    - Hart Leadership Program, 1980s-1990s (Box 9)
    - List of Research Centers and Programs Affiliated with the Sanford Institute (as of July 2008) (Box 9)
  - Southeastern Institute of Medieval and Renaissance Studies, 1967, 1969 (Box 9)
- Others
  - Continuing Education
    - Ederhostel, 1978 (Box 9)
    - General, 1970s-ongoing (Box 9)
    - Handbooks, 1973-ongoing (Box 9)
    - Publicity releases, 1969-1974 (Box 9)
    - Ten Years of Experience at Duke report, 1969-1979 (Box 9)
  - Honors Program, circa 1933-1978 (Box 10)
  - Nursing, School of
    - Administration, 1930-1978 (Box 10)
    - Brochures, 1953-1985 (Box 10)
    - The Charge (handbook), 1964/65, 1966/67 (Box 10)
    - General, 1980s-2000 (Box 10)
  - Parapsychology Laboratory, 1940-1980s (Box 10)
  - Parapsychology Laboratory - Publications, 1949-1980s (Box 10)
  - Spanish Studies, School of, 1943-1955 (Box 10)
  - Summer Session - Administration, 1920-1978 (Box 10)
  - Woman's College
    - Administration, 1930-1972 (Box 10)
    - Forms, memos, regulations, etc. (Box 10)
    - History (Box 10)
    - Memorabilia (Box 10)